Okay בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is בבא מציעא Bava
Metzia 103, קג. kuf gimmel. We pick up at the bottom of
קב עמוד ב, kuf bais amud bais, nine lines from the bottom.
We'll double back a little bit. בעי מיניה מרבי ינאי, Bo'ei minei
me-Rav Yannai, and we're working off of the משנה Mishna that was
discussing renting an apartment, whether you do it or a house, whether
you do it by the month or by the year.
בעי מיניה מרבי ינאי, Bo'ei minei me-Rav Yannai, שוכר אמר נתתי משכיר
אמר לא נטלתי. socheir amar nasati, maskir amar lo natalti. The renter,
let's say the tenant, says I already paid the rent, and the
owner says no you didn't.
Who do you believe? על מי להביא ראיה? al mi le-havi re-aya?
Who has the burden of proof? Now that's a little bit strange
because we normally say המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav hare-aya.
The person that is coming to extract money from somebody else, you
want to make me pay, you have to prove
that I owe you the money. It's a classic case of כופר
הכל. kofer hakol.
You say I owe you a hundred dollars, and I say even
though let's say I admit
that there was a debt, yes I owe you but I paid
you up.
Unless you have a שטר, shtar, I'm believed, I'm a כופר הכל,
kofer hakol, you're the המוציא מחבירו, hamotzi mechavero, you're the one who
has the burden of proof. So why would that be different here?
Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says אימת, eimas, when is this? אי
בתוך זמנו, ei be-soch zemano, if it's during the time in the
middle of the month before the rent is due, so תנינא, tanina,
we taught that in a משנה, Mishna, as we'll see, that clearly
the owner of the property is believed that the tenant has not
prepaid the debt. אי לאחר זמנו, ei le-achar zemano, if it is
once the rent is due, תנינא, tanina, we also taught that in
a משנה, Mishna, and as we'll see the indication being that once
it's due, you assume it has been paid. Where do we get
this from? דתנן, de-tanan, we taught in the משנה, Mishna, this is
about a case of פדיון הבן, pidyon haben, which you do with
a newborn son, first son, on the after thirty days. So
מת האב בתוך שלשים יום, meis ha'av be-soch sheloshim yom, now what
if the father died before the thirty days were up and now
the son is an adult and the son wants to ask the
rabbi am I obligated to do פדיון הבן? pidyon haben? The question
is, do we think that the father did it or not? So
if the father died within thirty days, then the presumption is he
did not yet do the פדיון. pidyon. בחזקת שלא נפדה עד שיביא
ראיה שנפדה. bechezkat she-lo nifda ad she-yavi re-aya she-nifda. You have to
assume the father didn't pay the thirty, he wasn't obligated yet to
pay it, unless you can bring evidence that for some reason he
decided to do a פדיון הבן pidyon haben before thirty days. Now
this is fascinating, it makes it sound like a פדיון הבן pidyon
haben can be done and would be good if being done before
thirty days, we won't get into that, that's a whole discussion when
we get to בכורות, Bechoros, but this sounds like it would be
good, but you just presume that the father wouldn't have done it
yet because he wasn't yet obligated. Okay, people aren't going to pay
money before they're obligated. לאחר שלשים יום, le-achar sheloshim yom, if it's
after thirty days, בחזקת שנפדה עד שיאמרו לו שלא נפדה, bechezkat she-nifda
ad she-yomru lo she-lo nifda, then the son has to assume, should
assume, that he's not obligated in פדיון הבן pidyon haben anymore, he
should assume once it was thirty days and the father died on
the thirty-first day, then he should assume the father did the מצווה,
mitzvah, once the obligation came the father did the מצווה, mitzvah, he
should assume the מצווה mitzvah has been done, until he gets a
report, עד שיאמרו לו, ad she-yomru lo, like the neighbors or whatever
tell him no no no your father we know he was planning
on doing it later but he didn't get to it before he
died. But without that type of report, he should assume that the
father did the מצווה. mitzvah. So here you see, within thirty days
we assume, during the time before the debt comes due, we assume
it hasn't been paid; once the debt comes due we assume it
has been paid. Now it's a pretty strange proof because this is
a question about do I have a ritual obligation of פדיון הבן?
pidyon haben? Nobody can actually sue me, the idea of על מי
להביא ראיה, al mi le-havi re-aya, we're not dealing with the ממונות,
mammonus, no particular כהן Kohen do I owe the money to. So
if I want to do the מצווה, mitzvah, we could say that
after thirty days, before thirty days I should presume it hasn't been
done and I should play it safe and I should do the
מצווה. mitzvah. That, or after thirty days I can presume not. But
that doesn't necessarily mean what would be the story if somebody were
trying to demand the money from me and I wasn't interested in
doing a מצווה mitzvah and I was claiming
that I had already paid,
that might just go back to the normal principles of המוציא מחבירו
עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav hare-aya. So it's a little funny that
the גמרא Gemara thinks that this is directly relevant. Let's see where
the גמרא Gemara goes with this. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
צריכה ביומי דמשלים זמניה. tzericha beyomei de-mashlim zemanei. No, we're talking not
in the middle of the month, and we're talking not after the
last day of the month, we're talking during the last day of
the month. All right, it's the rent isn't due till tomorrow or
till tonight at midnight, but today is the last day. So בעי
עביד איניש דפרע ביומי דמשלים זמניה או לא. bei avid inish de-para
beyomei de-mashlim zemanei o lo. Is it that people are, is it
that it sometimes happens that people pay up on the very last
day? Yes, technically they're not obligated but sometimes, it's already due later
today, you'll pay up today. אמר ליה רבי יוחנן, Amar lei Rabbi
Yochanan, so Rabbi Yochanan responded, תניתוה, Tenitua, we taught that as well,
okay, coming up later on. So שכיר בזמנו נשבע ונוטל. Sakhir bizmano
nishba venotel. It's a משנה mishna later about you know, things that
they did, really it's a משנה mishna in שבועות, Shvuos, about special
תקנות takanos that חזל Chazal did to allow somebody to take a
שבועה shvua and to collect money. The normal הלכה halacha in the
תורה Torah is כל הנשבעין, kol hanishba'in, you know, נשבעין ואין משלמין,
nishba'in ve'ein meshalmin, that when the person who takes the שבועה, shvua,
you take the שבועה shvua to say that you've paid your debt,
whether it's a מודה במקצת modeh bemiktzat or an עד אחד, ed
echad, whatever the case might be, and then you don't pay. So
you take the שבועה shvua and you're פטור. patur. But there are
a few cases where חזל Chazal
saw
fit to say no, the person making the claim against you can
take the שבועה shvua that you owe them the money and they
can collect. So one of those cases was a worker because
you know, you have a daily worker and he's coming for his
wages and he says I haven't been paid yet and you say
you have been paid and neither of you has a proof. So
normally again that would be a classic מודה במקצת, modeh bemiktzat, he's
demanding his wages, you say I paid you, and you should take
a שבועה shvua and be פטור patur and be exempt. Or not
even take a שבועה—דאורייתא you don't even take a שבועה shvua by
a כופר הכל—excuse kofer hakol me, I said מודה במקצת, modeh bemiktzat,
that's a classic כופר הכל, kofer hakol, you're denying everything, so you
wouldn't even have to take a שבועה דאורייתא. shvua de'oraisa. דרבנן Derabanan
you take a שבועת היסת, shvuas heses, but you would be exempt.
But they said in the case of workers since you have, if
you're the בעל הבית ba'al habayis of let's say a field and
you have a hundred hired hands, you can't be paying attention to
everybody exactly who you paid or not, and it's more likely that
you got mixed up and you forgot that you paid him than
that he is the one making the mistake. So if he's willing
to take a שבועה, shvua even though this should be a כופר
הכל kofer hakol and you shouldn't have to pay, they allowed him
to take the שבועה shvua, and to collect. שכיר בזמנו נשבע ונוטל.
Sakhir bizmano nishba venotel. So שכיר, sakhir, you know, if it is
still during the time in which the paying is going on, he
can go ahead and he can take and he can take and
he can take the שבועה, shvua okay, if it's still like during
the time in which the paying is going on. So this word
בזמנו, bizmano, the גמרא Gemara in שבועות Shvuos explains means that it's
you know the day in which the wages are due. Because since
it's a תורה Torah prohibition about הלנת שכר halanas sakhir that you
cannot let the night go without paying the wages, we assume that
in order not to transgress that prohibition, the בעל הבית ba'al habayis
is going to make sure and pay attention to who exactly he
paid and who he didn't pay. But on the day itself that
it's due before that time period has passed, then he is too
busy and distracted. So they allowed the hired hand to make the
שבועה. shvua, All right, so that's a similar case, the day in
which the wages is due, do we assume it's been paid or
not? And it's only because of a special תקנה takana about the
בעל הבית ba'al habayis being distracted, you know, that we actually say
that you can take a שבועה shvua. and collect. So that's what
the גמרא Gemara says.
שכיר הוא דרמו רבנן שבועה עליה משום דבעל הבית טריד בפועליו. Sakhir
hu deramu rabanan shvua aleia mishum deba'al habayis tarid befo'alav. In the
case of a hired hand, you know, of a day laborer, they
said they allowed the person to make the שבועה shvua to collect
because the בעל הבית ba'al habayis is distracted. Now here it is
the owner of the property that is trying to collect from the
tenant, you know, and for somebody to be, so the tenant only
has one person he owes the money to, he's not distracted. So
there would be no reason to switch it from the דאורייתא de'oraisa
principle that the owner of the property is a, what do you
call it, is making a demand, the tenant is a כופר הכל,
kofer hakol, he's denying everything, he's not distracted. So the הלכה halacha
is המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה.
hamotzi mechavero
alav hara'aya. אבל הכא שכיר מהימן בשבועה, Aval hacha sakhir meheman bishvua,
but he would have to make a שבועה. shvua רשי Rashi says
that's just the standard שבועת היסת shvuas heses that חזל Chazal required
even by a case of a כופר הכל. kofer hakol. All right,
so in the end the גמרא Gemara basically says it's basically a
straight case of a כופר הכל, kofer hakol, you make a שבועה
shvua. and you're off and off the hook. However, what is fascinating
is is that it does sound like that's only on the last
day where it sometimes happens that it gets paid. But prior nobody
is going to prepay
the rent in the middle of the month. Or if you would,
then you would get a clear receipt to prove that you have.
So it actually sounds like this חזקה chazaka that people would not
prepay the rent in the middle of the month, you don't pay
before it's due, would override המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, hamotzi mechavero alav
hara'aya, and you know, and if you went around claiming in the
middle of the month that you've already paid the rent, you wouldn't
be believed, you would have to bring a proof to that fact.
That is certainly what the גמרא Gemara sounds like. Okay, אמר רב
אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav amar Rav Nachman, four lines from the
top, האי מאן דאוגיר ליה ביתא לחבריה לעשר שנין. Hai man de'ogir
lei beisa lechavreia le'eser shanin. Somebody rented a house to his friend
for ten years. וכתב ליה שטרא, Vechasav lei shtra, and he wrote
on the שטר, shtar, you know, that I am hereby renting you
this property for ten years.
And but it didn't say... say what the start date was. Whoops.
ואמר ליה נקיטת דחמש שנין va-amar leh nekitat de-chamesh shanin and he
says you've already been on it for five years, you only have
five years left. And the guy says no, I've only been a...
חמש שנים chamesh shanim מהימן meheiman he's believed. Okay and the other
guy says no, like I've been on it only one year or
two years or three years. So let's see why that is true,
why is he believed, right? Basically what it means is that, you
know, is that he's going to be able to...
Oh no. And presumably it's a case where, you know, the full
rent has been paid for the ten years. So basically I'm trying
to give you only five years left and you're claiming that I
owe you seven years more on the money that you've paid or
let's say the debt will be due at the end of the
time but it doesn't matter, nobody's debating they're going to pay me
$10,000 whether you paid it at the beginning of the ten years
or at the end of the ten years. But right now, so
I'm getting the money that we agreed upon, but I'm claiming I
only owe you five years more left of usage and you're saying
I owe you seven years more left of usage. So let's see
how the גמרא Gemara understands it. The interesting question again, who's the
המוציא מחברו? ha-motzi me-chavero? So it says you believe the owner of
the property. אמר ליה רב אחא מדפתי לרבינא, Amar leh Rav Acha
mi-Difti le-Ravina, אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, אוזפי מאה זוזי בשטרא, ozfei me'ah
zuzei bi-shtara, ואמר ליה פרעתיך פלגא, va-amar leh paraticha palga, הכא נמי
דמהימן? hacha nami de-meheiman? Let's say somebody went ahead and borrowed a
hundred dollars and there was a שטר shtar written that, you know,
you owe me a hundred dollars, and then you say I paid
half. You wouldn't be believed, right? Because I have a שטר shtar
and the שטר shtar says you owe me the full amount. As
long as I'm holding on to the שטר shtar that says you
owe me the full amount, you owe me the full amount. You're
not believed to say you paid part. So why isn't this similar?
Why isn't the tenant saying I got a שטר shtar that says
you owe me ten years of use of the house? You're saying
you gave me five years of that use. I'm saying you didn't.
So I'm totally believed. I have the שטר shtar and I should
be able to collect, use it for the full ten years. If
I say only seven, fine, then seven years. Okay, but look at
that document as if I am coming to extract usage of that
property and I have the שטר shtar and I should be believed.
הכא נמי דמהימן? hacha nami de-meheiman? אמר ליה Amar leh he said
back to him, הכי השתא, hachi hashta, what type of a comparison
is that? התם שטר לגוביינא קאי. hatam shtar le-guvaina ka'ei.
There, when I write a document that you borrowed a hundred dollars
from me, the purpose of this document is to use to collect
the loan. אם איתא דפרע im ita de-para and you know, I'm
going to use this as evidence that you owe me the money,
and you know that if you pay me up, full or part,
you're going to need to get some counter-evidence. You're going to need
something to do to counteract my evidence. אם איתא דפרע איבעי ליה
למכתב אגביה. im ita de-para ibayei leh limchtav agabei. If then if
you actually paid me up fifty, you're going to insist that we
write on the שטר shtar fifty has been paid.
אינמי מכתב ליה תברא inami michtav leh tavra you're going to want
a שובר, shover, you're going to want a receipt for the fifty
that you've paid. Okay, because you know I'm going to have evidence
and I'm going to use it to collect the full amount, so
you're going to need counter-evidence if you've paid it up partially. אבל
הכא aval hacha but in this case where the tenant has a
שטר shtar that says he's owed ten dollars... ten years. What's the
goal of that? Is the goal of that to be able to
constantly prove that he has ten years rights and that the owner
of the property would always have to collect receipts in order to
counter-prove it? Is that how the שטר shtar is functioning as evidence
that he has ten he can demand ten years? No, that's not
why it's written. האי דכתב לך שטרא כי היכי דלא תחזיק עליה
hai de-chtav lach shtara ki heichi de-lo tachzik alei that it shouldn't
become like a חזקה chazakah because now you're going to claim that
you were on, you know, you were on this property, my property,
for three years and I sold it to you, and therefore because
that's the whole principle of חזקה chazakah in בבא בתרא, Bava Batra,
and I'm going to say no, you weren't, it wasn't yours, I
didn't sell it to you, you were a tenant and we have
a שטר shtar to bring evidence to that. Which raises an interesting
question of who's holding on to the שטר, shtar, because if the
tenant is holding on to the שטר shtar he could tear it
up. Okay, but maybe, I don't know, maybe there are two copies
of the שטר. shtar. It's a fascinating question about who's holding on
to it. But the גמרא Gemara says the purpose of the שטר
shtar here is not evidence that the ten years has not been
paid up. The purpose of the שטר shtar is to clarify what
the role of you are, you know, is on the property. You
know, nowadays we could also imagine why do people sign leases? So
that so that I can't, if I'm the owner of the property,
I can't kick you out within the ten years, or that you
as the tenant, you know, or if you want to leave, maybe
you're committed to me to pay the full amount. So it serves
other purposes and it's not used to prove that I owe you
ten years. So it doesn't serve as that type of evidence that
needs counter-evidence. And therefore we just don't know how many years have
been used up. The שטר shtar isn't a relevant piece of data
for that. And it gets back to the principle of המוציא מחברו
עליו הראיה. ha-motzi me-chavero alav ha-ra'ayah. You with the שטר, shtar, you're
trying to claim seven years of use. I'm the one who the
קרקע karka is in my possession as the owner and I say
it's only five years. You have the burden of proof. Okay. אמר
רב נחמן. Amar Rav Nachman. Okay,
so now we’re going to end with some things that don’t seem
totally related to our משנה, Mishnah, but actually seem a little more
connected to the next משנה. Mishnah. אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman,
שואל אדם בטובו לעולם. Shoel Adam Betuvo Leolam. If somebody says, "Lend
me, you know, your, I don’t know, your shovel בטובו, betuvo, while
it’s good, in its good state," okay, then that actually I have
rights now to use it until it breaks, because the word בטובו,
betuvo, this is quite fascinating, seems like it’s a way of taking
advantage of people when they’re doing you a favor, but when I
say בטובו, betuvo, it means as long as it remains good and
functional, you know, lend it to me. That’s how it’s being read.
Fascinating. Okay. אמר
רב מרי בריה דרב שמואל, Amar Rav Mari Berei DeRav Shmuel, והוא
דקני מיניה, Vehu Dekani Minei, only if you did a קנין, kinyan,
a סודר, sudar, which makes it actually like long-term binding. Now what
רש"י Rashi actually says is that’s only once you returned it. That
as long as you’re holding onto it, you can say, "Hey, you
lent it to me while it’s good, so I have indefinite use
of it while it’s good." But once you’ve returned it, to now
say you have a right to borrow it back because, "Oh, you
said I have a right to it while it’s good," for that
you need there to actually have been a, like to have been
a קנין סודר, kinyan sudar, for there actually have been something that
seems, shows like it's an ongoing commitment that you have this right
to use it whenever you want and not just for that one
transaction of me giving it to you before and until you give
it back. Okay, so that's that. אמר רב מרי בריה דרב אשי,
Amar Rav Mari Berei DeRav Ashi, so Rav Mari the son of
Rav Ashi said, ומהדר ליה קטי, Umehadar Lei Katei, and because you
said while it’s still good, then means you give it back to
him until it breaks,
literally. You, when you return it, you return it in its broken
form. Okay. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, האי מאן דאמר ליה לחבריה, Hai
Man Deamar Lei Lechaverei, a similar, a similar story. Somebody said to
his friend, אושלן מרא למירפק בה בי פרדיסא, Oshlan Mara Lemirpak Bah
Bei Pardaisa, "Lend me a, you know, a shovel that I can
use to dig with האי פרדיסא, Hai Pardaisa, this, this orchard." So
you only have rights to use it for that orchard, not for
another orchard. פרדיסא, Pardaisa, if you said, "Lend me, like allow me
to use it for a shovel for an orchard," so רפיק ביה
כל פרדיסא דבעי, Rapik Bei Kol Pardaisa Devaei, you can use it
for whatever orchard you want. If you have an orchard that’s a
hundred acres, גזונטהייט, Gezunteheit, you didn't specify, so you have the right
to use it for, but only for one. Okay. כל פרדיסא דבעי.
Kol Pardaisa Devaei. Now if you say פרדיסאי, Pardaisai, "Lend me this
for that I can use it for shoveling for my orchards," רפיק
ואזיל כל פרדיסא דאית ליה, Rapik Veazil Kol Pardaisa Deit Lei, I
can use it for all of my orchards, even if I have
them in a different country. Who knows? That’s the parameter. So basically
what it sounds like is that the combination of these two, well
one is a little limiting, "my orchard," you can't automatically assume that
you can use it for a different orchard. If you say singular,
"this orchard," you can't assume. So sometimes it can be limiting, but
sometimes it can be, we’re prepared to interpret it very expansively. And
again, presumably because it's right now in your possession, of the possession
of the שואל. shoel. It's not explained, doesn't say that, but that
might be a factor here. Okay. דבעי ואזיל כל פרדיסא דאית ליה,
Devaei Veazil Kol Pardaisa Deit Lei, ומהדר ליה קטי, Umehadar Lei Katei,
and then you can return it finally, you know, you can use
it till it breaks and it's like a מתה מחמת מלאכה. Meta
Machmat Melacha. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa, האי מאן דאמר ליה
לחבריה, Hai Man Deamar Lei Lechaverei, אושלן האי גרגותא, Oshlan Hai Garguta,
"Lend me this גרגותא," garguta, which is like a well, not a
cistern, a well, meaning there's live water feeding into it. You know,
"Lend it to me, let me use your well so that I
can, you know, irrigate my
plant." ונפלה, Venafela, and then the well collapsed. You know, you had
a whole structure around the well and it collapsed into it and
it would have to be redug or something in order to continue
using it. So לא בני לה, Lo Bani Lei, I don’t have
a right to say, "Look, you gave me the right to use
your well and it's now unusable. I want to dig it back
back up so I can continue using it." No, I don’t have
the right to do that because the well meant, you know, in
its current state. If you were to redig it, it would be
a new well. Now if you said, "Lend me גרגותא," garguta, you
don't say "this well," "Would you lend me your well that I
can, you know, that I can water my plants?" ונפלה, Venafela, and
it fell down, בני לה, Bani Lei, I have a right to,
I have the ability to rebuild it and you, and so what
if it’s a different well? I said, "Lend me a well." You
have agreed to let me use a well of
yours. Okay. ונפלה בני לה. Venafela Bani Lei. בי גרגותא, Bei Garguta,
if I say, "this area of
wells," so כרי ואזיל כמה גרגותא בארעא עד דמתרמי ליה, Kari Vaazil
Kama Garguta Beara Ad Demitrami Lei, then even if, you know, that
well collapsed, I can go ahead and within this area where the
wells were, you would have to figure out what's defined as that
parameters, maybe you had more than one well, I could keep on
digging and digging until I hit water because I said the place
of the wells. So that gives me that right. וצריך למיקני מיניה,
Vetzarich Lemikni Minei, but that's only if you did a קנין סודר,
kinyan sudar, because otherwise, right, and this is as opposed to when
I actually lend you an object that as soon as
you
land, then you didn't take it into your possession, then it's just
like a promise. I agree to let you use my well, well
you know what I can back out on my promise at least
from a legal perspective. The only thing that would make that legally
binding and give you legal rights is if you did a קניין
סודר. kinyan sudar. Alright, so what we have here though is cases
where when things are lent, we are prepared to interpret them pretty
expansively,
or maybe we try to
obviously we try to work within the parameters of what the language
means, but if it works within the parameters of the language, we're
prepared to be pretty expansive once the borrower gets it in his
possession, either through a קניין סודר kinyan sudar or through physically taking
it into his possession. Let's see the last משנה mishna and you'll
see how this גמרא gemara is really connected a bit to this
last משנה. mishna.
המשכיר בית לחברו, Hamaskir bayis lachaveiro, if somebody rents a house to
his friend, ונפל, venafal, and the house fell down, חייב להעמיד לו
בית, chayav l'ha'amid lo bayis, he has to replace the house. You
know, this guy's paying rent for a house, he has the right
to a house, I agreed to rent him a house. היה קטן
לא יעשנו גדול, Haya katon lo ya'asenu gadol, גדול לא יעשנו קטן,
gadol lo ya'asenu katon, if it was small don't make it big,
if it's big don't make it small, I mean unless he agrees,
but if he doesn't agree he could say, look, you know, the
heating costs are bigger if it's big, if it's small obviously I
have less space. אחד לא יעשנו שנים, Echad lo ya'asenu shnayim, שנים
לא יעשנו אחד, shnayim lo ya'asenu echad, if it was two rooms
don't make it one, one don't make it two, you can't assume
that you have to give him the same type of thing he
borrowed and he or he rented from you unless he agrees otherwise.
לא יפחות מן החלונות ולא יוסיף עליהם אלא מדעת שניהם, Lo yifchos
min hachalonos velo yosif aleihem ela b'da'as shneihem, and similarly you can't
have fewer windows, hey I like the view, or you can't have
more windows, you know I don't know it's letting too much sun
in, it's giving people too much access, you can't make any of
these types of changes unless both of them agree. So now let's
take a look, גמרא, gemara, היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's the case
that even if the house falls you have to replace it? אי
אמר ליה בית זה, Iy amar lei bayis zeh, I'm going to
rent you this house, נפל, nafal, if it fell, אזלי, azlei, then
the house no longer is around. Yes, you rented this house, now
it's a fallen house, I didn't promise to rent you an abstract
house, I promised not promised I committed we contracted to rent you
you know this particular house. אי אמר ליה בית סתם, Iy amar
lei bayis stam, that I rented the rental agreement just says I
am renting you a house and it didn't say specifically which one,
so then אי אמר ליה בית סתם, Iy amar lei bayis stam,
so אחד לא יעשנו שנים, Echad lo ya'asenu shnayim, קטן לא יעשנו
גדול, katon lo ya'asenu gadol, then okay that explains why I have
to now find a place for you or rebuild it because I'm
contractually obligated to rent you a house, not necessarily this specific one,
but what obligates me that it should be in exactly the parameters
of the first one? It's just an abstract house, so the same
way that creates an obligation on me after it falls, it should
also give me the freedom to decide what type of a house.
So the גמרא, gemara, at least certainly if it's going to be
bigger than the first one, interestingly the גמרא gemara specifically picked those
examples. אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, says Reish Lakish, דאמר ליה
בית שאני משכיר לך מדתו כך וכך, de'amar lei bayis she'ani maskir
lecha mido kach ve'kach, that you say the house I am renting
you you know I'm renting you a thousand square foot house apartment
or ten thousand square foot apartment. So therefore when you specify the
size of it, that requires you now since you didn't say this
one, if it falls you have to replace it, you said a
house, but since you said the square footage you have to replace
one of a similar square footage. אי הכי מאי למימרא, Iy hachi
mai l'meimra, so the גמרא gemara says if that's true, you explicitly
said the square footage then obviously you have to keep to that,
what's the משנה mishna telling you? I mean it might be telling
you you can't do more unless he agrees. אלא כי אתא רבין
אמר ריש לקיש, Ella ki ata Ravin amar Reish Lakish, דאמר ליה
בית כזה אני משכיר לך, de'amar lei bayis kazeh ani maskir lecha,
that you say I am renting you a house like this particular
one. So the fact that you said like and not this particular
one means that if it falls you have to replace it, rebuild
it or get him another one, but because you said but the
like makes it meaning in the same parameters. Still the גמרא gemara
says ואכתי מאי למימרא, ve'achti mai l'meimra, so what so you didn't
say ten thousand square feet, saying like this obviously then that's all
very clear then that's what you're obligated to. לא צריכא דקאי אגודא
דנהרא. Lo tzricha d'kaya guda d'nahara. No it's coming because what it's
coming to say that let's say it's on a river bank, you
know beautiful view, you got a river view. מהו דתימא, Mahu d'teima,
מאי כזה דקאי אגודא דנהרא, mai d'kazeh d'kaya guda d'nahara, קמשמע לן.
kama'ashma lan. So I might have thought that you are required you
know to do it to specifically replace one that has a river
view so this is to no excuse me you could read this
גמרא gemara two ways. רש"י Rashi reads it לחומרא. l'chumra. I might
have thought that it suffices to replace one with a river view
but it doesn't have to have the square footage. The משנה mishna
comes and teaches that no it also has to have the square
footage. You could have read this גמרא gemara the river view is
not part of it, it's all about the square footage, but רש"י
Rashi reads it no the river view is not enough, you also
need the square footage. Again, I would have just thought that the
חידוש chiddush of the משנה Mishnah is that you can't do it
bigger because but okay. הדרן עלך השואל. Hadran Alach Hashoel. That's the
end of השואל Hashoel and now we go back to a new
פרק perek where again we get back to themes about hiring laborers
and so on. המקבל שדה מחברו: HaMekabel sadeh m'chaveiro: so somebody basically
takes the responsibility from somebody else. Somebody owns a field, ראובן Reuven
owns a field, and
שמעון Shimon takes on the field to work it. There's two ways
in which he can take on the field to work it: either
he can rent the field from ראובן, Reuven, pays that's called חוכר,
chocher, pays him an annual fee for the use of the field
and he's going to plant it and harvest and he'll keep all
the harvest to himself. Or he could be a sharecropper, that he
doesn't give ראובן Reuven particular fixed amount of money, but he, you
know, spends all the expenses, he plants, he harvests, etc. and ראובן
Reuven gets a percentage of the crops. We'll see that classic percentage
might have been a quarter of the crops. Okay. So המקבל שדה
מחברו מקום שנהגו לקצור יקצור לעקור יעקור. HaMekabel sadeh m'chaveiro makom shenahagu
liktzor yiktzor la'akor ya'akor. So what do you do after the crops
have been harvested with the stubble at the bottom? So some places
they would actually or let's put it this way, you know,
would it be enough to cut the wheat and you could leave
the stubble at the bottom, that's לקצור, liktzor, that you just do
classic harvesting, or would you have to actually uproot and you know
pull them out the stubble, pull it out from the very roots
from the ground? So it says you follow whatever the practice is
and no one can neither the owner of the field or the
person working on the field who's rented it has the right to
change unless they both agree. לחרוש אחריו יחרוש: Lachrosh acharav yachrosh: and
if the practice was to plow over, you know, plow the field
after you're done with the harvest to get rid of the weeds
or the grass or whatever, then you have an obligation to do
that. הכל כמנהג המדינה: Hakol k'minhag hamedinah: it all follows whatever the
standard practice is. כשם שחולקין בתבואה כך חולקין בתבן ובקש: K'shem shecholkin
bitvuah kach cholkin b'teven u'v'kash:
the same way in a case of a sharecropper they divide the
grain, they also divide even the stubble and the straw because you
know that also could be used for animals or whatever. That's included.
כשם שחולקין ביין כך חולקין בזמורות ובקנים: K'shem shecholkin b'yayin kach cholkin
b'zemorot u'v'kanim:
and the same way if it's the case of a vineyard they
divide the wine and the grapes, they also divide any of the
prunings that they made from the
you know from the vines ובקנים u'v'kanim and the קנים kanim which
the גמרא Gemara will say is like the trellises. ושניהם מספקין את
הקנים: U'shneihem mesapkin et hakanim:
now why the trellises? Normally all of the expenses are on the
person that's working it, the sharecropper, but because both the owner and
the practice was that both the owner and the sharecropper would pay
for the trellises, would jointly pay for the trellises, so when it
came to be the end of the year and for whatever reason
I guess you would you know make it new each year, they
would also therefore equally split the wood of the trellises. Let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says.
תנא: Tana: we taught, מקום שנהגו לקצור אינו רשאי לעקור לעקור אינו
רשאי לקצור. makom shenahagu liktzor eino rashai la'akor la'akor eino rashai liktzor.
Okay, that's our משנה, Mishnah, ושניהם מעכבין זה על זה. u'shneihem me'akvin
zeh al zeh. And here it's telling you it's not just restricting
one of the parties, either party can say I don't accept that
you're doing something against the מנהג minhag because there's ways in which
each practice could be beneficial to one or detrimental to the same
person. There's a plus and a minus on each side to both
parties. So let's take a look. So either party can object. ושניהם
מעכבין זה על זה למה לי לקצור אינו רשאי לעקור. U'shneihem me'akvin
zeh al zeh lamah li liktzor eino rashai la'akor. So if the
practice is to you know to harvest it with a sickle or
whatever you're not allowed to uproot it from the roots. האי אמר
בעינא דתתבן לי ארעאי, Hai amar beina d'titban li ara'ai, because the
owner of the field could say no, I insist that you don't
uproot, I want to use the stubble to feed my, I want
the stubble left on the ground, I want to feed my animals.
והאי אמר V'hai amar and similarly if the owner wants to insist
it gets uprooted the person who's on the field could say לא
מצינא לעקור. lo matzina la'akor. I don't want to go to the
effort of uprooting, it's so much easier to just harvest with a
sickle. So each one has the right to object.
לא מצינא: Lo matzina: I'm not able to, I you know I'm
not that's too much effort. לעקור אינו רשאי לקצור: La'akor eino rashai
liktzor: so if it's now the flip, let's say the practice is
to uproot then either party can object to trying to switch it
to harvest with a sickle. Why? האי אמר בעינא דתנקר ארעאי: Hai
amar beina d'tinakeir ara'ai: the owner could say I insist you do
the normal practice of uprooting, I want my land to be clean,
I want all the stubble removed.
והאי אמר בעינא תיבנא: V'hai amar beina tivna: and so now how
come the person on the field can insist to do the uprooting
if the owner wants him to do the harvesting? Because he can
say yeah the uprooting is more effort but it gives me the
straw and because he's a sharecropper or he's a renter, you know,
he gets all or some of the straw so I insist we
do the uprooting so that I can get some of the straw.
ושניהם מעכבין זה על זה למה לי: U'shneihem me'akvin zeh al zeh
lamah li: so now once you've said that you know each side
can object and you basically said you know you're not allowed to
change makes it clear that there's a plus and a minus on
each side. Why do you have to again repeat that both of
them can object? It's already implicit from saying you're not allowed to
change. So מה טעם קאמר? Ma ta'am ka'amar? מה טעם לא רשאי
לעקור לעקור לא רשאי לקצור. Ma ta'am lo rashai la'akor la'akor lo
rashai liktzor. It's telling you why you're not allowed to change. You're
not allowed to change משום דשניהם מעכבין זה על זה mishum deshneihem
me'akvin zeh al zeh because each side has a reason, has a
legitimate reason to object and therefore if anyone does object you're not
allowed to, you're not allowed to change unilaterally because because because you
cannot say oh this is going to benefit the owner. No, each
side has a reason to object so without the consensus you can't
change it. Okay. לחרוש אחריה יחרוש. Lachrosh achareiha yachrosh. If the practice
is to plow afterwards you plow afterwards. פשיטא? Pshita?
Obviously. לא צריכא באתרא דלא מנחשי. Lo tzericha be'asra dela menachshei. It's
in a place where they would not go by hand and pull
out the weeds and all they would do would be plow. והאי
דאזיל
איהו ומנחש Vehai de'azil ihu umnachesh and now the person, the renter,
the sharecropper goes and he uproots, is uprooting you know at an,
you know he's been uprooting all along the weeds with his hands.
And now there's a few little weeds sprouting up, but basically he's
uprooted everything with his hands all along the way, put in a
lot of effort. And now he
says I don't want to bother plowing now. מהו דתימא אמר ליה
האי דנחשי ארעא דלא כריבנא לה? Mahu deteima amar lei hai denachshei
ara'a dela kareivna lah? He says look, the whole reason I was
uprooting all along with my hands the weeds is so I wouldn't
have to plow afterwards. קא משמע לן דאיבעי ליה לפרושי ליה. Ka
mashma lan de'ibei lei lefarushei lei. So this teaches you no, if
that's what you wanted you had to say explicitly I'm going to
uproot it, I'm going to uproot the weeds by hand on the
condition I don't have to plow afterwards. But you cannot assume that
your actions can work to undermine the standard practice unless you explicitly
stipulate against them. הכל כמנהג המדינה. Hakol keminhag hamedina. Everything goes by
the standard practice. הכל לאתויי מאי? Hakol le'atuyei mai? What's that come
to include? לאתויי הא דתנו רבנן, Le'atuyei ha detanu rabanan, what our
Rabbis taught. מקום שנהגו להשכיר אילנות על גבי קרקע משכירין. Makom shenahagu
lehaskir ilanos al gabi karka maskirin. Let's say there are trees that
are, you know, in this big field that's used for planting wheat,
there are some apple trees. Okay. So and we don't specify whether
you, the person who has the sharecropping rights or you the person
who's rented it, are you, do you get to keep the apples?
So it says if the standard practice is to let the person
on the land keep the apples, if he's the renter then he
gets all the apples, if he's a sharecropper he gets the proportion
of the apples, but he doesn't have to really work the apples,
so that's a nice bonus. So if that's the practice then מקום
ש makom she then he gets it. מקום שאינו נהגו להשכיר אין
משכירין. Makom she'eino nahagu lehaskir ein maskirin. Places where it's not assumed
to go along with the land then he does not get the
rights to it. So now the Gemara is going to unpack this.
מקום שנהגו להשכיר משכירין פשיטא? Makom shenahagu lehaskir maskirin pshita? Obviously if
that's standard then of course he gets it.
No. לא צריכא דכולי עלמא יהבי בתילתא ואזיל איהו ויהיב בריבעא. Lo
tzericha dechulei alma yahvi besilsa ve'azil ihu veyahiv beriv'a. That normally everybody
gives,
the owner of the land gets a third of the crops in
a case where it's a sharecropper, a third of the harvest. And
they made a stipulation, there are apple trees on the land and
they made a stipulation that he'll only keep a quarter of the
profit, much you know, the owner gets less. מהו דתימא דאמר ליה
האי דבצרי לך אדעתא דלא יהבת לי באילנות? Mahu deteima de'amar lei
hai debatzi lach ada'ata dela yahvas li be'ilanos? So the owner could
say why do you think I agreed to give you, to only
take a quarter and not to take my standard third? Because implicitly
I didn't want you to have rights to the trees okay and
all the apples are mine. And that's why I took a quarter
rather than a third. קא משמע לן דאיבעי ליה לפרושי ליה. Ka
mashma lan de'ibei lei lefarushei lei. No, even though logically that might
make sense the מנהג minhag is the מנהג minhag and the standard
practice is assumed to take place unless you explicitly stipulate against it.
מקום שנהגו שלא להשכיר אין משכירין. Makom shenahagu shelo lehaskir ein maskirin.
Now the reverse. If the practice is that the person working the
land does not get the apples then he doesn't get the apples.
פשיטא? Pshita? That's obvious. לא צריכא דכולי עלמא מקבלי בריבעא ואזיל איהו
וקביל בתילתא. Lo tzericha dechulei alma mekabli beriv'a ve'azil ihu vekabil besilsa.
It's the reverse of the previous case. The standard is that the
owners get a quarter and the sharecropper here agreed to give the
owners a third.
מהו דתימא אמר ליה האי דטפאי לך ארעא דתיהב לי באילנות? Mahu
deteima amar lei hai detafai lach ara'a desiyav li be'ilanos? I would
think the sharecropper could say the reason I gave you a bigger
a larger portion, a third rather than a quarter, was on the
assumption that I would get to keep the apples. קא משמע לן
דאיבעי ליה לפרושי ליה. Ka mashma lan de'ibei lei lefarushei lei. You're
not, that doesn't matter, it doesn't work. If you want to go
against the standard practice you have to say it explicitly. כשם שחולקין
בתבואה כך חולקין בתבן ובקש. Keshem shecholkin bisevu'ah kach cholkin beteven uvakash.
Going back to the Mishna the same way they divide the grain
they also divide the straw and the stubble. So the Gemara says
אמר רב יוסף בבבל נהוג דלא יהבי תבנא לאריסא. Amar Rav Yosef
beVavel nahug dela yahvi tivna le'arisa. In Babylonia the standard practice was
that the sharecropper does not get the, does not get the straw.
It's not a הלכה. halacha. The Mishna is talking about standard practice
as we see. Standard practice is always what dictates so in בבל
Bavel the standard practice is different. למאי נפקא מינה? Lemai nafka mina?
The Gemara says what do I care? I already know that principle
that הכל כמנהג המדינה hakol keminhag hamedina so you know it always
goes by the מנהג. minhag. So why why like why are you
telling me what it is in בבל Bavel if I ever have
to If I ever have to deal with something in בבל, Bavel,
I'll find out what the standard practice is in בבל. Bavel. So
the גמרא Gemara says no, דאיכא איניש דיהיב עין יפה ולא גמיר
ממנהגא de-ika inish deyayiv ayin yafah ve-lo gamir miminhaga because even if
something is a standard practice, every now and then, you know, there'll
people which will go against the standard practice. So you can't go
ahead if you're a sharecropper and say, look, you know, your next-door
neighbor gives his sharecropper hey, Johnny's parents let, your next-door neighbor gives
his sharecropper straw, so I should also get straw. So no, I
want it to be clear that there are some people who act
differently, but the standard accepted that but when they act differently they're
just being generous, but it's understood that that's generosity, and it's understood
that the standard right is that he does not get the straw.
אמר רב יוסף Amar Rav Yosef בוכרא וטיפסא ארכבתא וכני דחיזרא דבעל
הבית. Buchra ve-tifsa arkavata ve-kanei de-hizra de-ba'al ha-bayit. So, the רש״י Rashi
says that these would be different like mounds of dirt that would
be constructed around a ditch that was grown that was dug around
the area of the what do you call it of the of
the field that was being worked. And the basic principle here is
that even though the sharecropper, we'll just assume it's a sharecropper, is
the one that has to pay for the manure and the effort
and do and the seeds, but the owner has to take the
expenses when it's about protecting the actual land itself. So building maybe
this was a type of mounds or whatever that small rodents couldn't
jump over, it sounds like. So that thing, the first mound בוכרא
Buchra is the first mound, טיפסא tifsa is like a second mound
build next to it, and ארכבתא arkavata is a third mound, וכני
דחיזרא, ve-kanei de-hizra, כני דחיזרא kanei de-hizra are like the sticks used
for the fence around it and like maybe the strings of, you
know, the fence, that דבעל הבית de-ba'al ha-bayit the owner of the
field has to provide that. וחיזרא גופיה Ve-hizra gufeh but the actual
thorns that they would weave into the strings, you know, around the
post, imagine you have posts and instead of barbed wire you would
use you would use some type of a you know you'd weave
in thorns, that would be the barbed wire with strings. So that,
that which is extra protection of the field to make them thorns
and not just basic protection, that's וחיזרא גופיה דאריסא ve-hizra gufeh de-arisa
the sharecropper provides. כללא דמילתא Klala de-milta the basic principle is כל
עיקר בלמא דבעל
הבית kol ikar balma de-ba'al ha-bayit the basic protection you know protection
of the land is on the owner, נטירותא
יתירתא netiruta yetirata any additional way to make it you know extra
safe and also to protect the crops, right, is דאריסא de-arisa that
is on the sharecropper. ואמר רב יוסף Ve-amar Rav Yosef מרא וזבילא
ודבלא ושבוא mara ve-zvila ve-davla ve-shavo and the זבילא zvila רש״י Rashi
says here
means the what do you call it זבל zavel which is so
זבל zavel means, you know, manure, it seems like we're talking here
about some type of a shovel used to move manure. So a
hoe, and I think the first one actually is more of a
hoe than a shovel. Okay so the the hoe and the shovel,
the manure shovel, ודבלא ve-davla and the pick, the bar- excuse me
the bucket for drawing water, וזרנוקא ve-zarnuka and the זרנוקא zarnuka which
רש״י Rashi says is, you know, is like a more of a
flask used for drawing water, דבעל הבית de-ba'al ha-bayit that is on
the owner. So this seems like it's more like the equipment, right?
The manure itself, the seeds itself, that would be on the on
the sharecropper, but providing the equipment, that's on the owner. דבעל הבית
De-ba'al ha-bayit אריסא עביד בי יאורי arisa avid be yaorei but the
it is the sharecropper who has to go ahead and and dig
like irrigation canals from the main river to get to the to
get actually to the field itself. So the equipment and some of
the stuff that's basically there about the gates around the field, you
know, it's always the question you rent an apartment, what part is
the landlord obligated for, what part is you obligated for, so this
is the standard division of this, of course it would all be
shaped by the מנהג המדינה. minhag hamedinah.
Okay, last section, כשם שחולקין ביין כך חולקין בזמורות ובקנים. keshem she-cholkin
beyayin kach cholkin bizmorot uvakanim. קנים מאי עבידתייהו? kanim mai avidtaihu? What
do you mean the קנים kanim which normally might sound like it
actually means the sticks of the vines itself, but you're not cutting
down the vines themselves. So אמר דבי רבי ינאי amar de-vei Rabbi
Yannai קנים המחולקים שבהן
מעמידים את הגפנים, kanim ha-me-chulakim she-ba-hen ma'amidim et ha-ge-fanim, no, like split
rods or whatever that the the vines grow on, mean that we're
talking about the trellises. ושניהם מספקין את הקנים Ve-shneihem maspikin et ha-kanim
and both parties provide the wood for the trellises. למה לי? lama
li? Why do you tell me this? מטעם קאמר. ma ta'am ka-amar.
מה טעם שניהם חולקין בקנים משום דשניהם מספקין את הקנים. ma ta'am
shneihem cholkin bakanim mishum de-shneihem maspikin et ha-kanim. It's explaining the two
parts of the משנה. Mishnah. Why do they divide the wood of
the trellises? Because they both were the ones that provided the wood
of the trellises. Okay, let's take take a look at the משנה
Mishnah and get to the bottom of the page. המקבל שדה מחבירו
והיא בית השלחין או בית האילן Ha-mekabel sadeh me-chavero ve-hi beit ha-shlachin
o beit ha-ilan
so let's say somebody agrees to be a sharecropper, the גמרא Gemara
will discuss later which of these are sharecroppers and which of these
are חוכר chocher renters, okay, but this one is but the but
the משנה Mishnah we just did before is about both and this
would also be both. So some but we'll just say sharecropper because
it's an easier word. If the somebody is the sharecropper of a
field and it's a place that has a That, you know, does
not have enough rain, rainwater is not enough for it, but it
actually has a well in the field itself, okay, or if it
is a place that has trees, and as we've already seen, you
know, the trees are nice bonus for the sharecropper because he doesn't
have to work them and he gets their produce. יבש המעיין ונקצץ
האילן Yavesh hamayan v'niktzatz ha'ilan אינו מנכה לו מן חכורו. ayno menake
lo min hachikuro. Okay, if the well dries up or the tree
dries up and now he's not going to get the bonus in
the case to the tree, he's going to have to work a
lot harder in the case of the field to irrigate it. Nevertheless,
he cannot ask for a reduction.
חכורו Chikuro is in the case where he's a חוכר, chocher, where
he's a renter. So if he agreed to rent it for this
year for $10,000, he can't say, oh my god, now I'm going
to have to work harder, I don't get the bonus of the
apples, it should only be $8,000, that was worth $2,000 to me.
You're not allowed to say that. And similarly, if you're a sharecropper,
you can't renegotiate the percentages. It's just your tough luck. אם אמר
לו חכור לי שדה בית השלחין זו או שדה בית האילן זו,
Im amar lo chor li sade bait hashlachin zu o sade bait
ha'ilan zu, but if he mentions it and he says, I want
to rent this field of yours with the that has the well
in it, or I want to rent this field of yours that
has the tree in it, even though that might just be a
signifier, you know, an identifier, nevertheless because he mentioned it, that means
that that's part of what determined how much I was agreed to
pay in rent or the percentage of the sharecropping. So in that
case, יבש המעיין ונקצץ האילן מנכה לו מן חכורו. yavesh hamayan v'niktzatz
ha'ilan menake lo min hachikuro. So in that case, if those things
dry up, you do get a reduction in your rent because that
was clearly important for your agreement for that amount of rent. Okay,
so we will end with this, we'll pick up with the גמרא
Gemara tomorrow.